[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
all right everyone welcome to the stoa
i am peter limberg the steward of the
stoa and the store is a place for us to
cohere and
dialogue about what matters most at the
nice edge of this very moment
and um so for
some of the new faces here at the stoa i
don't know how to describe this space
but you know some people call it digital
campfire we have a wisdom gym component
where we get to practice all these
different muscles
that help us become more wise human
beings together
and all these interesting people are
coming on my radar
i'm reaching out to some someone
reaching out to me and i
forget how exactly um devaraj sandberg
came on my radar but he's pretty awesome
uh he's a therapist workshop leader and
writer and does something called
bioenergetics
um and if you're not familiar with that
uh uh devarash is going to give us a
kind of a one-on-one preview
on it and how today is going to work
this is a 75-minute session so sorry if
that wasn't indicated um
but the first 15 minutes are going to be
an introduction to bioenergetics
uh then the next 30 minutes is going to
be a guided bioenergetics
session uh so make sure you wear like
loose clothing have some room
and then the last 30 minutes will be a q
a and how that's going to work you have
any questions throughout
um maybe the 15 minute introduction
portion or anytime throughout the
um experience today put it in the chat
i'll call on you and mute yourself this
will go on youtube so if you don't want
to be on youtube just indicate that and
i'll read it on your behalf
um anything else i think that's
everything
uh that being said good morning my
friend
how you doing today you're a mute
let me unmute you
unmute okay i got it cool thank you
peter thank you for
inviting me on your platform and um
thank you for making such an awesome
platform as well you know
i read your emails in the morning and
you know i like this got balls man
it's good it's just good
and uh yeah so i'm going to talk a
little bit about um
bioenergetics basically and a little bit
about therapy
and particularly working with uh with
with the body
in therapy you know because it's kind of
like how i see it is like um
it's like when you're a little kid you
know there's like three things that you
kind of that are yours
and that continues you know as we see it
you know like you've got thoughts
you know we can think about things and
stuff like that and create ideas
and you know then there's like feelings
emotions
you know sadness joy anger
and then there's like the sense of the
body you know this kind of
what for a lot of people is just this
kind of slightly dull
kind of flooding feeling or something in
the background a little bit you know and
and when we look at therapy you know and
and different ways to kind of
deepen our deepen our experience or
develop or
let go of the past or or whatever you
know when there's a kind of calling
inside
either through something really bad
happening in our lives and we feel man i
need to sort this out
or or or just through you know you think
wow it must be more to life than just
working in this bloody job or whatever
and
people seek development in various ways
and mostly what they what we go to is
stuff working with forts
initially maybe you know a lot of modern
therapy you know from
even sigmund freud onwards you know the
1890s or
through the cbt cognitive behavioral
therapy dialectical behavioral therapy
this kind of thing
we're working with the thinking mind you
know
and and then maybe you know you get into
feelings as well you know certainly some
psychotherapists would
would you know they'll talk and they
want to create a connection with you and
then
and then you know bring you into deeper
feelings you know so emotions start to
come maybe they
they track what's going on in your life
now you kind of track it back to
your relationship with your dad or your
mom or stuff like this
and this is all great but what i kind of
and i did a bit of this particularly the
feeling stuff i did a lot of
work with feelings and screaming and
shouting in group rooms
all day and all night sometimes in
different osho places
uh but what i really came back to at the
end was just this kind of feeling of the
body
you know which kind of we all overlook
because
it's kind of dull or it seems kind of
dull or boring you know i think
you know when you're like young you know
thoughts are exciting experience is
exciting
you know going out into the world and
feeling stuff is really exciting the
feeling of the body is not
really such an exciting thing as as i
see it personally
but the feeling of the body is like also
it's your ground
in a sense and what i've discovered
personally and
and working with people the last decade
or so is
the more you as a general kind of rule
you know the more
you can actually feel your body
the more whole you are the more present
you can be
the more grounded you can be the more
in the kind of extremes of emotionality
without
completely getting hijacked and losing
it into behaviors
where later on you really regret stuff
and this practice of bioenergetics which
is a kind of body movement therapy
but the concept is basically just to get
body more open
and by that i mean
it's derived from originally in the west
the work of a guy called wilhelm reich
and here this idea of when traumatic
events happen or when we're just
conditioned a lot in childhood not
really allowed to just
be ourselves in some way that is all
held
in the body in the muscle system in the
fascia
as holding patterns you know areas of
unnatural tension in the body
or dead zones you know kind of like
areas where the awareness has just
dropped out and so
your personality is kind of represented
in your body
it's there in your body and whilst
like i say at the beginning you know
normally when we want to change our
personality or let go of the past
we go to our mind and you know we look
for therapists and stuff and we look for
stuff to do with our mind you know and
our thought patterns
and our behavior from our mind but
you don't have to go to that place or if
you've been to that place and it's not
really working
for you somewhere you can also just work
at a bodily level
you can actually just work at a bodily
level because
i mean what i came across you know about
a few years into my therapeutic journey
about 20 years ago my realization was
i'm just blocked
i'm just blocked as basically i'm
just completely
completely blocked and
you know actually all i need to do is
not think about who to be anymore
or or how to do this or how to get this
girlfriend or or whatever
you know like who do i have to please
who do i have to be
i just need to take out the blocks i
just need to take out the blocks
and and what remains will be will be me
you know will be more authentic version
of me
and you know this is what bioenergetics
really
to me is about it's got three elements
to it you put your body in a posture
sometimes it's a slight movement posture
or pulsing
and then you try and maintain the
posture and at the same time you breathe
through the mouth quite deep
because we're trying to bring energy or
or oxygen you know into the body into
the
into the main trunk core of the body
builds up a bit of a charge
of energy inside you breathe quite deep
and you try to keep your attention on
your body just feeling your body
and then with different postures and and
practicing this
what tends to happen over time is that
sometimes you go through like quite a
deep emotional process but
often you just feel more open it's like
this kind of holding patterns come a bit
to the surface
and sometimes people shake or whatever
then it starts to diffuse and move
and after doing bioenergetics
it's quite common you know what you want
you feel more grounded
you know like you're more you're more
present on the earth
but at the same time you're more open as
well it's like
it's okay to be open with someone you
know i realized
for the first time in my life i didn't
need to be in in total control of every
situation
you know which was my default
unconscious default
like as a as a kid growing up from my
childhood you know
and so this openness was really really
like miraculous to me and
with the groundedness as well there's a
sense that okay i can be open
but if something bad starts happening i
can protect my boundaries i can put
boundaries up
you know energetically and so a big part
of bioenergetics is really you're in
postures you're opening up the body
and you're allowing stuff to move
without needing to really think about it
so much the only
kind of job that your mind has
is just to try and maintain the posture
on the edge of your comfort zone
if it's really really painful then you
know you need to stop or slacking off in
some way if it's physical pain
to try and remember to keep breathing
because often people
they do a posture and they focus on the
posture but they shut their breathing
right down they kind
of close at the throat and then to try
and remember just to keep your awareness
on your body
you know and if you can the more that
you can keep those three going
stuff opens up another way that
bioenergetics works particularly
how i how i use it is is opening kind of
centers in the body
like most people are on a on a kind of
deep psychological level blocked at the
throat
you know their throat they don't feel
like it's okay to just
be me you know you know it's that it's
like been trained out of us
as a little kid i'm not saying everybody
but you know it's it's quite common in
my experience
and also people are kind of blocked they
can't feel their belly
you know so what happens when we can't
feel the kind of natural
somatic centers of the body is but the
mind kind of takes over
by that i mean like the prefrontal
cortex up here you know it just says
well i'm going to take over this job you
know i'll take over keeping you upright
and i'll take over protecting your
boundaries
you know and but it it invariably
when it's trying to do this you know it
just makes the body tense basically so
so yeah it kind of does it but it
creates a lot of tension
in in doing it you know so
being able to feel your spine you
realize like oh i i'm okay
you know i can i can be upright on the
earth i don't have to just
wobble all over the place and and please
people
or or fit in or whatever you know when
you can feel
your belly you know it's like okay i
have energy i have power i've
had that sort of animal power center you
know and uh
i can protect my boundaries if i need to
i can really
you know be male aggressive if i need to
you know so it's like we're opening up
energy centers
and we're freeing up areas that are held
basically in the body
you know and that's i guess it's kind of
a way of explaining bioenergetics i just
give
you know because it's kind of common in
the uk at the moment but there's a lot
of people talking about embodiment
you know and it's okay a friend of mine
wrote a book about embodiment recently
and runs his conference
and there's another guy uh i wonder if
his name was always banging on about
embodiment but
there's a kind of irony for me but
they're not necessarily really working
their body very much
you know they're just writing lots of
stuff about embodiment
and maybe i really is not quite the
right word but
what we're trying to do in bioenergetics
is is bring the awareness out of his
thinking mind for a while and let it
kind of start to reoccupy the body
you know to occu instead of having to
i see in the world you know a lot of
people want change and they're they're
fighting against
stuff out in the world a few years ago
there was this occupy movement you know
where
people are super pissed off about this
thing in london so they occupying this
area i think it was in wall street as
well or something and
but what struck me was like if you're
occupying your body
you know you don't necessarily need to
see the issues in the outside or
it can be a kind of default mode of the
brain
to perceive the issue on the outside
when actually it's more internal
and that's not to say that you can't
ever protest or
or it's not authentic to protest but
it's kind of like a default mode of the
brain particularly when you're young
like in your 20s
but it's like a teflon coating the ego
so
internal stuff is just tends to be
disowned and we just see it in the
outside world you know like
men are wrong you know and
you know authority is wrong you know
it's just like
because we had a bad experience of
authority as a kid
you know when that that that repressed
feeling starts to vibrate a bit it's
like
suddenly the world is wrong you know the
world is wrong i really need to
just i'm weak i need to get together
with like-minded people and oppose it
you know it's like how the brain
functions and uh
the problem is is that if if maybe the
issue is internal
then you're not really doing yourself
any favors and you could be empowering
yourself by feeling more
i did this a lot when i was young you
know i was a total conspiracy theorist
and i was
massively resentful of authority i was a
punk i was a squatter i lived on the
street
you know i was a druggie and i just
basically assumed that all authority was
wrong and needed to be opposed
on an ongoing basis you know because
that was kind of how i processed my
my relationship with my adoptive father
but
you know what happened at a certain
point for me in my 30s was
this teflon coating of my ego kind of
faded away a bit
and i started to feel and and i
started to realize
whoa what if it's me what if it's me you
know all these things i've been fighting
in the world
what if it's just what if it's just me
and my childhood you know
so that's when i kind of got involved in
therapy
anyway since this is a little bit
rambling i don't know if i've quite uh
quite um introduced enough
but i was thinking maybe we just do some
do some body work basically and all
you'll need is some
relatively loose clothing i'm not going
to do any of the kind of noisy stuff
uh because you might be in an
environment where you can't make a ton
of noise
but we're gonna just work our body a bit
and
i think i can just talk our way through
it my tripod's been a bit of a mess and
i need to just kind of
i don't know how to get it so that i can
see myself a bit bigger
maybe like this maybe not anyway
i'm going to turn it around a little bit
just can you guys see me okay
yeah okay okay
i can you can hear me okay at this kind
of volume level
uh yeah it's not as great but we can
still hear you okay
okay cool um what we're gonna do
so stand up basically stand up because
you're not just going to be watching me
and make sure you've just got like a
little space around you like a few
square meters
and then for a moment just take your
feet about shoulder width apart
and and bend your knees a little bit so
you're not locked through the knees
and just start to maybe close your eyes
and just feel your body
just breathing however you want to
breathe and just
just feeling this body
for a long time i just saw this body as
a kind of vehicle like a car
that my mind could drive around in
and i still do at times but
actually it's an amazing amazing
resource
and then just have a few steps around
your space trying to just remain feeling
your body
and what i'm going to do actually is put
on a gene track just to work with about
a minute and a quarter long
and we're just going to go through some
exercises when there's a ding
we'll change the exercise you just keep
breathing and feeling your body
i'll sort this bean track out
so the first exercise we're going to do
is a kind of a
pulse suggest you gently interlink your
your fingers behind your back and you
kind of move your
move upwards like this if you can see
this okay
not so you're getting just like a
pulsing movement you can tap your
tailbone
as our first ding you can walk around
with this if you like
but just gently pulsing upwards
and now we're going to start to breathe
through the mouth while we're doing this
fairly deep and really have the
intention just to stay in the body
feeling what's going on
breathing in and out through the mouth
charles keeping this pulsing going being
aware of any ache
breathing through the mouth
and with again just let it go give your
arms a little flick
then come into another pulsing movement
put your palms together in prayer
position but pointing backwards
with your upper arms vertical and we're
just going to pulse like this
pointing back pointing up
and again if you wish you can walk
around a little or just stay with your
knees a little bent standing
pointing back pointing up and again
breathing through the mouth and feeling
feeling your body
ah breathing out nice and deep
and if you're standing checking that
your knees are a little bent but you're
not locked through the knees
and then letting that go with the ding
and now we are going to come to standing
about with your feet about shoulder
width apart or a little more
drop your ass slightly so that your
knees are a bit bent back
your back is upright and we're going to
pull the shoulders forwards
so you don't need to use your arms as
levers they just kind of follow but
you're pulling your shoulders forwards
like you're trying to get your shoulders
to touch
in the middle of your chest which you
almost certainly won't be able to do but
you're just
you're doing that and you're breathing
through the mouth make sure you breathe
out
and you just feel your body and you
maintain the stretch
pulling the shoulders together so the
stretches in the shoulders
the arms are kind of just following
along
nice big breaths in and out through the
mouth not holding your breath
and then we're going to do a camera
stretch which is stretching your
shoulders
back imagine you've got like a walmart
between your shoulder blades
and you're trying to crack it keep your
knees a little bent
really squeeze back and breathe
yeah breathe out squeeze those shoulders
together and breathe
if any of this really gets physically
painful and you don't feel like
like it's good for you then just lay off
don't do it so much but otherwise try to
breathe through any discomfort
breathe out
and there you go with the ding do you
get your arms a little if you want to
and staying in this body position pull
the shoulders up towards your ears
so the movement is in the shoulders your
arms just kind of follow
pulling the shoulders up towards the
ears kind of like you're auditioning for
frankenstein or something or
one of those assistants of frankenstein
that always opens the door and stuff
pulling the shoulders up towards your
ears like you're trying to get your
shoulders to touch your ears
and breathe big breaths breathe
maintain the stretch breathe through the
mouth
and just feel what's going on in your
body just
feeling it
ah
oh breathe out
and let it go
and the next one is a little different
we're going to keep the lower body in
this position
and we're going to do a fake smile so
and really make it visible so
it's literally allowing the corners of
your mouth come up towards
your eyes compressing your cheek muscles
like you've got a job in american hotel
chain on the front desk you just have to
smile all day
you're gonna get the sack
keep your mouth a little open so you can
breathe through the mouth
really work those muscles
corners of your mouth up towards the
eyes you should feel it in the cheek
muscles
stay with it keep it up
and there you go move your face around
if you want to shake your
arms a little bit and the next one's
also with the mouth this time we're
going to open your mouth
wide wide as you can like a teenager
trying to
eat a triple triple burger in one
mouth wide open really stretch that jaw
try to keep
it fully wide until the ding breathe
through the mouth and feel your body
and there you go and now bring your feet
to
shoulder width or maybe a little bit
closer together we're going to go into a
bowl position
bring your arms right up palms facing
forwards
and then squeeze your arms back so you
feel a compression in your shoulder
blades
and at the same time push your pelvis a
little forwards
you're kind of trying to make your body
shape like an arch as like an archer's
bow
but with your head keep it upright
and again breathe through the mouth and
feel
your body
stretching into this bow shape but
keeping your your gaze level
head upright stretch those arms back
behind the ears
press that pelvis a little forwards
big breaths out through the mouth
and let your body straighten bring your
arms down i'm going to do a counter
stretch called the
arch posture feet closer together like 6
8 inches
15 centimeters hang forwards
when you're hanging forwards don't go
down so low that your fingers reach the
floor
but just off the floor jiggle your arms
and your head a little bit to make sure
you're not knocking in the neck or the
shoulders
imagine your ass muscles are being
pulled up with straightening your legs
while keeping a little flex in the knees
and just breathe through the mouth and
feel your body big breaths
uh
and then slowly uncurl your body coming
back up
your head comes up last and that was a
wrap and we're going to do
another rep move the camera a little bit
so we're going to start straight off
with this
arms behind your back and pulsing like
this
again with this right now you're getting
used to it
really breathe big breaths and feel your
body
you don't need to to to make any kind of
narrative about how it feels
you just that act of just really feeling
your body
is giving love to this body that we
often
don't really cherish i didn't cherish it
for a long time
knees a little bit bent
pulse and breathe pulse and breathe
breathe through it
and now arms up and we're going to do
this reverse prayer pulsing gesture
again keep those knees a little bent and
really breathe through the mouth
don't hold up the throat to survive
just breathe deep
pointing back pointing up stay with it
and breathe your way through
aim to breathe your way through
discomfort and if it really becomes
physical
physically painful then stop oh
oh
and once again let it go and
stand with your feet at least shoulder
width at least shoulder width apart
bend both knees shoulders front
pulling the shoulders together big
breaths through the mouth
maintain the stretch breathe through the
mouth
feel what's going on
oh
yeah pull those shoulders see if you can
get another millimeter closer
and breathe through big breaths
so your breath is audible
and let it go shake your arms a second
and then shoulders back right you've got
that
wall now between your shoulder blades
and you're trying to crack it
keep those knees a bit bent
keep your ass down a little bit breathe
through the mouth
stretch and breathe
see if you can get those shoulder blades
another millimeter closer check it out
yeah squeeze a little more keep that
breathing audible
um
and let it go with the tin
shoulders up towards the ears right up
pull those shoulders up and breathe
big breaths it's the action of
stretching and breathing at the same
time and feeling what's going on but
allows holding patterns to start to
release
keep those out breath so you can hear
them
keep those knees a little bent don't
lock through your knees
ah yeah breathe out
maintain the stretch and breathe
and let it go have a little shake
and then we're coming into these mouth
stretches so really go for it
fake smile big fake smile
in england we would say that californian
fake smile i don't know if you're
allowed to say that
in america
feeling a squeeze in your in your cheek
muscles
nice a little open so you can breathe
through the mouth keep that smile going
like you're just loving it
feel what's going on in your body as you
smile it's a powerful
taoist and biologic exercise
[Music]
and let it go
do what you need for a moment and then
we're going to do jaw stretch
mouth wide open wide as you can big wide
mouth
like you're a 15 year old you want to
get that triple burger in one
one bite triple veggie burger if you
imagine
check that stretch little bit wider can
you get it a little bit wider
mouth wide open
i'm gonna let it go and we're gonna come
round into our bow posture
so our arms are up palms facing forwards
and then stretch the arms back
and then press your pelvis forwards
keeping a little flex in the knees
keeping your gaze level your head
upright
stretch breathe feel
and then straighten the body relax the
arms bring your feet closer together
and hang forwards
take it slow if it feels a bit much on
your lower back
hanging forwards breathing through the
mouth
oh
uh
and coming slowly back up feeling your
body as you can
news i think we've got time for a third
rep good news for the
body bad news for the mind maybe
we're going to start with this pulsing
movement again
breathing and feeling so take your
fingers behind your back
and just breathe your way through
it's natural to have a bit of mental
resistance
the trial breathe your way through
i'm going to make this rep a little bit
shorter
keep helping keep breathing from the
mouth nice and deep
you can do it
we're going to be on shoulder jeans for
this one
big breaths out particularly if you're
struggling a little bit
really breathe out
and then let it go and bring your arms
up into this
reverse prayer pulsing movement
pointing back pointing up keeping your
upper arm
relatively vertical and static
cool
really breathe in some air big breaths
physical
and breathe it out
um
and let it go take that nice quiet
grounded stance
and bring your shoulders to the front
and breathe
and really give them a little squeeze
bringing those shoulders closer big
breaths
make your breathing really audible
oh
and let it go and bring the shoulders
back
keeping that ass down a little bit
yeah squeezing back and breathe big
breaths
remember if it's really going into
physical pain you need to lay off
otherwise try to breathe through the
discomfort
keep that squeeze going like you're
trying to break that that walnut between
your shoulder blades
and breathe your way through you can do
it
relax for a moment and then shoulders up
right up high
right up towards those ears stretches in
the shoulders so your arms are just kind
of hanging following along however they
are
pull those shoulders right up and
breathe deep breaths
try not to lock up the throat try not to
go into survival mode
just try to breathe your way through
breathe out let it go last few postures
fake smile
pull the corners of those mouth up high
high as you can
squeeze into those cheeks and breathe
and feel
yeah a little bit see if you can get it
a little bit higher
and breathe
um
and let it go with your face for a
moment you need to
and then jaw stretch be wide mouth wide
as you can
big mouth
um
and let it go background into your
posture for the last time
arms right our palms facing forward
stretch the arms up
and then stretch from back behind the
ears compressing the shoulder blades
press your pelvis forwards keep your
knees a little bent
breathe through the mouth and feel your
body
and then relaxing your body a second
bring your feet closer together
and hang forwards into the arch posture
and then coming up we're just going to
do something to to integrate a little
so please take your feet to shoulder
width apart again and bend your knees
and then feel into your legs and see if
it's like a slight trembling happening
and if there isn't just gently shake
your body
you can close your eyes if you wish or
keep them open
we're just going to let the body shake a
little
for a couple of things
keep breathing and feeling into your
legs
have your palms facing a little towards
the front
opens the body and if you like you can
lean very slightly backwards and see if
the shaking comes
it's up to you
spontaneously
stay with it
you
and then for two more things if you'd
like to just sit down somewhere and
close your eyes
and just breathe normally and feel your
body you can sit on the floor
on a cushion on a chair whatever just
take two minutes just to breathe and
feel your body sitting
eyes closed please
just keeping your attention on your body
breathing normally
and just staying like this for one more
doom please
um
so now it's time just to open your eyes
if you want to
come back to the room
have a little stretch
and uh it's like a question time i think
very cool i feel my uh body vibrating
internally
so if you have any questions start
throwing them in the chats
we have about 15 minutes um of q
a uh one thing that
caught my attention when you're talking
and doing that exercises is
mentioning the internal like mental
resistance like when we're going to the
third
like kind of um third round and i'm like
like i had that like oh do i have to do
this
uh and i did these in toronto these
bioenergetic classes and some of the
poses they put you in man is really
painful um
so do you have any kind of uh heuristics
or techniques in order to deal with the
mental
uh tension and and the bodily attention
that occurs during these
i mean you know there's lots of
different bioenergetics teachers in
different schools and whatever and
if it goes into physical pain i usually
tell people to stop
basically you know uh or
just lay off you know but if it's just
discomfort then try to breathe your way
through
and assuming it is just discomfort and
basic mental resistance
like i've just done two reps of this i
don't want to do another rep it's enough
now
you know that's that kind of mental
resistance will come up in a lot of
areas of your life usually often when
you're stepping up or trying to do more
of something
and so it is actually really useful
practice in a broader perspective just
to say okay let's just do a
i've got my resistance i'm going to do
it anyway and just breathe my way
through
because it's kind of like a mental
holding pattern
that's moving
all right um does that help i'm not sure
if it quite answers
yeah yeah that that that did help um
so let's go to we'll go to a little
question a moment but uh anja and i
think that would be a good question to
kick start off the
q a portion hey there raj
um i feel like somebody rubbed
uh rub a535 over my body i have this
like
minty tingling over me what
what the hell happened how how does this
work
well it's kind of a writing thing in a
sense that you know when you start to
charge your body with energy by
breathing through the mouth in and out
you know then you you
you start to what happens is it kind of
creates a little bit of friction between
the energy that's stuck in the body you
know and this is kind of reiki and
theory and stuff
and the fresh energy that you're
charging up with and stuff comes to the
surface and you might feel
tingling you might feel heat you might
feel not so much you might
find parts of your body going numb even
you know it's all sorts of
things that can happen i don't know if
there's a really hard uh proper
scientific explanation for it that there
might be
i don't i don't really know but it's
basically a good sign
you know
because the body is meant to be
vibrantly alive in my opinion
you know it's the whole body should be
behind what we're saying what we're
doing
what we're feeling you know the body has
neural potential all around it you know
but we're
kind of this little bit up here has kind
of taken over control
you know like a really bad 1980s style
boss
and it's just demanding the rest of the
body does what it wants
no it's what's happened in a lot of
people's lives so this tingling and
vibrant aliveness and emotional kind of
fluidity
is like is a good thing if you ask me
i hope that helps um do you have a
comment on what the shaking was because
i felt that a lot on the bow
one um very it was very visceral
yeah i mean the body does does
shake i mean i don't have a neurological
kind of explanation for it or something
like that
but one of the things you're doing
particularly in the bow posture is
you're starting to
you see as you charge your body with
energy maintain the stretch
by holding patterns it's like it's like
you've got a dishcloth you know a
dishcloth that you find under the sink
you know it's gone all stiff and hard
you know and
by putting liquid on it like awareness
in a kind of metaphorical sense and
squeezing it around
it starts to be compliant again so by
holding it starts to be released
basically physically as heat as
vibrations whatever
so you're kind of stretching muscles out
of their normal
zone basically it's like this but you're
taking something that's a bit
held and rigid stretching it more than
you normally would
you know and it starts to vibrate and
release the holding
basically especially when you're
breathing through the mouth to charge
your body with more energy as well
all right uh lily you had a question
lily are you still in this room
maybe not um
[Music]
all right let's go to uh zach
then we'll circle back to lily in a
moment
you want me to verbally ask yeah yep
um yeah my question
is why these exercises
um why do they seem to why does and and
range of motion seem to
be part of the the recipe and you kind
of already touched on that
what was the last i missed a little bit
of that sentence sorry zach
yeah like i'm just i guess i'm i'm
wondering
like why these exercises and why do the
exercises seem to all be
kind of taking us to like end range of
motion like is there something about end
range of motion
that yeah
i mean special yeah it's just one it's a
set of exercises
a lot of them are working around the
shoulder area you know
and um one thing you know
if you ever had a feeling of deep grief
you know that it's like the heart
on an energetic level opens here you
know it's like something bursting open
and in similar manner this energetic
heart you know it closes between the
shoulder blades
basically so when you start to work the
area between the shoulder blades quite a
lot
often it does bring feelings a bit to
the surface you know emotions
that have kind of been held down a
little bit start to just come up
but you know in bioenergetics you know
there's all sorts of different postures
and you're working all different parts
of the body i just
did that sequence because i actually did
it in a class a week ago and i thought
i'll do that one
um my second question is
like what would you recommend as like a
dose
if someone wants to do this like as a
regular practice how might they know
they're doing too much
and how might they know that it's like
working
you know well i would say you know
you've got start off slow and
you know some people like to get really
excited about something and charge into
it doing tons and then kind of drop it
real quick
and that doesn't really work with this
kind of practice so
it's good to do something like maybe
even 10 minutes if you can commit to 10
minutes just to those last two postures
bow and arch
you know maybe like on a one or two
minute ding
and just see how that goes and and just
just do 10 minutes in the morning if you
can fit that in and just just see how it
goes record
you know record how you you feel
afterwards or how your day goes
you can always check out my channel on
youtube for more postures i've also got
a book and
an online course and stuff like this you
know but you could just start with like
10 12 minutes it's a good length of time
to do it
it's not really you know what makes the
difference is when someone can kind of
get into it for a longer period
which usually means that they are
getting some positive benefit
and but then they can kind of stick with
it at times when it's a little bit of a
struggle and stuff like that
all right i'm going to read lily's
question uh
where is it why breathing through the
mouth
i can pay more attention while breathing
through the nose is it about letting go
of control
and i'll take on a comment from mary as
well and
mary said curious about choice of open
mouth breathing versus yogic
mouth closed and then maybe another
comment from area
um usually a more quiet person found
self-releasing sounds during
exercises curious about that
yeah i mean often people do yoga too to
calm down and get peaceful
you know so breathing through the nose
will usually support that
you know breathing improve the nose and
out through the mouth is quite quite
common in yoga but
with this technique we're not you know
you may well feel calm afterwards but in
the practice you're not really trying to
just calm yourself
you may find it soothing but breathing
through the mouth generally
kind of creates more raw energy in your
body in the in
in the core of your body you know
breathing quite deep and
this creates a charge which works to
start to help
help the release happen so although kind
of you know quite a quite a few of the
postures might look a little bit like
yoga and may even be the same as yoga
the kind of mental attitude and and what
you're doing with the breath is a bit
different
it's a bit different so you know it's
basically to charge your body with
energy
as opposed to trying to relax the body
you know you actually
in order to create relaxation in this
kind of way of
this kind of approach you're actually
over stretching or stretching very
strongly
some of the muscle groups and you know
through doing that they can release some
of that holding that's sitting there
that doesn't really get to move when
they're just doing their usual range of
motion
and then it starts to come out and then
when you do sit down later you feel wow
like i'm really
now i'm really relaxed so that's the
kind of theory basically
i'll read this comment uh for you you
can use this as a testimonial maybe
uh damn i was so skeptical while we were
doing it seemed dumb
but damn i feel so relaxed and
tingly right now it seems like i just
got a two hour massage
you gotta you went over a skeptic um
cool thank you sarah uh you're up next
okay um have you heard of uh trauma
releasing exercises
um a i felt an urge to shake even before
you kind of invited that
and i found that the shaking was a i
preferred it it was a lower frequency
like
bigger movement bigger muscles than the
kind of high
that i often get in the theory
yeah yeah trauma releasing exercises
came out about i don't know about 20
years ago
15 20 years ago this guy david picelli
and i mean he never says this but as i
understand it it's like a small subset
of kind of diverse bioenergetic
exercises
that he you know he kind of trademarked
it and copyrighted it and created
a training for it you know so
i think it's pretty cool i mean
bioenergetics is
is pretty extensive and kind of
sprawling and not really under control
by any kind of
governing body if you have tried but
they have not
really succeeded uh so
you know tre is a much more kind of
formal structure you've got certain
exercises and that kind of thing
but my experience of tr is mostly based
on what i would call bioenergetics but
you know i don't
you know i'm not trying to make some
kind of uh
uh you know kind of um competitive point
or
you know that kind of thing it's not you
know tiara is great
bioenergetics is generally worth it can
go in a lot of different directions
do you have a follow-up sir
not really thanks oh i'll i'll just i'll
just follow
that up so so when i hear all this stuff
what i actually said whether it's
bioenergetics whether it's tre whether
it's osha or whether it's shaking
but the whole purpose of all this stuff
is to just move
energy so and then the body has to find
out
what actually suits the body it could be
yoga yoga might not be strong enough it
might be screaming
um so one way or another we're simply
making
manage energy move is that is that the
case and we have to find out what
actually suits us
yeah i mean i guess you know with a lot
of these kind of practices and
different therapies in general you know
it's kind of like
when you first start off you're kind of
like walking around a mountain and
trying different paths
you know and at some point you have to
kind of choose a path and just keep
going with it you know
that's how i see it i mean a lot of your
show kind of working
dev raj is not sure name you know uh
you know yeah was focusing on on
catharsis on the body on feeling the
body
breathing and some very kind of intense
process work that was around in the 70s
and 80s which has mostly
kind of disappeared now but the stuff
like the shaking is kind of remaining
all right um let's go to margaret
this is probably our last question
hi thank you deb raj um
i'm curious oh man sorry i started
talking and woke the baby um
why um what you see is the unique
offerings of bioenergetics
versus other somatic breast practices
you touched a little bit upon mentioning
yoga as a tool for relaxation
but i guess i'm just when i hear all
this it kind of sounds like rebuilding
the wheel
so i'm curious as to what you see as the
unique offerings of this path as you put
it through the mountain
well yeah i mean um i would say you know
with bioenergetics it's kind of it's
specifically focused
on removing the kind of bodily effects
of trauma or conditioning
basically you know there are some
secondary focuses and different slightly
different things
but that's its kind of primary focus and
you know you may well get a similar
effect doing yoga particularly say
ashtanga or something like this
but it's not actually been created with
that intention
you know hashtag yoga you know it's
about developing the asanas and
developing your body to be a fit vessel
for hindu spiritual practice
traditionally usually
but with bioenergetics it's been
specifically created
to start to take out some of the blocks
as they manifested were accessible at a
physical level
that was that's what it specifically
intended for so
you know there's hundreds of other
techniques which may resemble it a bit
but they don't have that specific focus
and that's kind of useful in a secondary
way because
then people are coming to it with the
express
intention that that is what they want to
do and when you have the intention okay
i want to get
you know i've got this trauma from my
dad or my mom or
this or that writing character type or
whatever you have a specific intention
to move through that
and then that having that level of
intention also supports you
you know as where like for example when
i started to do therapy and i needed to
do really heavy therapy but i started
going to like
dance workshops because i thought maybe
like five rhythms would get rid of it
you know or whatever you know and maybe
i'd meet some women as well or something
you know it was like i wasn't really
addressing you know there's nothing
wrong with dance workshops they're great
but
i was not really addressing but i needed
to do actually very deep therapeutic
work
to heal from what had happened when i
was a kid you know so
there is something about calling it a
therapy and
and saying this is what it's
specifically about but it tends to pull
in people who
are ready at an ego level to really okay
i really want to start to work on this
you know they're not kind of being
wishy-washy with their mind anymore like
i could do a bit of that do a bit of
this you know
interesting i really appreciate the
framing around intention
um and conscious intention because i
think that is
although available in other uh
thematic-based tools
um not necessarily as you said with
their primary purpose and creation
so that does help frame it in terms of
this as a tool for this
specific thing or domain
thank you cool thank you
awesome um so we're going to close out
here
i thought this was a really fun session
and a great introduction to this
modality so uh thank you for that um any
closing thoughts you'd like to leave us
and where we can find you and
and your other work yeah sure
you can find me on youtube if you look
for devaraj bioenergetics
instagram too and i have a website
bioenergetics.org.uk
uh and you know i got a book and all
those kind of game a things you know
and an online course and all that kind
of stuff you know which is pretty cool
it's like
the online course is quite intense it's
for people who really want to commit for
one or two years or
got that but it's uh you know you learn
an awful lot about bioenergetics and go
on a big
kind of online journey uh
yeah thank you for going for it guys the
ones i could see looked like they were
really getting into it so
that on on the zoom thing so thank you
everybody
and thank you peter for inviting me it's
much appreciated
awesome yeah thanks for coming and then
come back anytime i would love to have
you here
at the stoa um and just to plug a couple
of
events uh in about 45 minutes
um just gonna meet someone about 45
minutes we have embodied book club
the collective presence thing uh you'll
have to read the first two chapters so
if you haven't done that
maybe come the week after and you can
read it's a six week session
we're actually going to practice and
read the book at the same time this is
uh with uh
ria bach um riabek and then
[Music]
empathy circle training with edwin rutch
this is like a gamification of carl
rogers active understanding with
four people edwin the inventor of this
modality is going to come in
and train this is going to be at the
memetic mediator campfire this is for
four weeks
and if you take 10 at least three
sessions then you uh
are eligible to get be a trainer and do
some training with with edwin
so that should be fun um we have tons of
events on the website
uh we have a wisdom gym we have one-offs
so you can go there we have a patreon if
you'd like to support
and uh sub stack you can follow my
misses and daily musings
uh so that being said uh dev thank you
so much for coming
everyone thank you so much coming for
thank you everybody thank you peter